<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Testimonium Jesu, or, The demonstration of the spirit for the confirmation of Christian faith, and conviction of all infidelity a sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and aldermen of the city of London, at the Guild Hall-Chappel / by Bryan Turner.</title>
            <author>Turner, Bryan, 1634 or 5-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08259107</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08259107</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41255</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63872)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41255)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1242:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Testimonium Jesu, or, The demonstration of the spirit for the confirmation of Christian faith, and conviction of all infidelity a sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and aldermen of the city of London, at the Guild Hall-Chappel / by Bryan Turner.</title>
                  <author>Turner, Bryan, 1634 or 5-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. Roycroft for Walter Kettleby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XIX, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:41255:1"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>WARD Mayor,</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Martis XXV<hi rend="sup">to</hi> die</hi> Januarii, 1680. <hi>Annoque Regni Regis</hi> CAROLI <hi>Secundi,</hi> Angl', <hi>&amp;c.</hi> xxxii<hi rend="sup">do</hi>.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>UPon the motion of Sir <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> Kt. and Alderman, This Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> to print his Sermon, ſometime ſince Preached at the <hi>Guildhall-Chappel</hi> before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41255:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>TESTIMONI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>;</hi> Or, THE Demonſtration of the Spirit, FOR The Confirmation of Chriſtian Faith, and Conviction of all Infidelity. A SERMON Preached before the Right Honourable THE LORD MAYOR and ALDERMEN OF THE City of LONDON, AT THE GUILDHALL-CHAPPEL. By <hi>BRYAN T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER,</hi> B. D. Rector of <hi>Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne, Oxon,</hi> and Chaplain to the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, <hi>CHARLES,</hi> Earl of <hi>Carliſle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by S. <hi>Roycroft</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettleby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-yard,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:41255:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41255:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>REVEL. XIX. 10.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And I fell at his feet to worſhip him, and he ſaid unto me, See thou do it not: I am thy fellow Servant, and of thy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that have the Testimony of Jeſus: Worſhip God,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the Teſtimony of Jeſus is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Prophecy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether St. <hi>John</hi> here was through Joy tranſported into too ſubmiſs a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; or, he miſtook the Perſon for Chriſt, (as the Angels telling him who he was, ſeems rather to inſinuate,) is not needful to determine.</p>
            <p>If tranſported into too ſubmiſs a Reverence, ſuch as was uſually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate to Divine Worſhip; then it reads us this Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, That on the one hand, <hi>Bodily Adoration</hi> is within the liſt of Divine Worſhip, and neceſſarily due by the Commandment, <hi>Worſhip God:</hi> and on the other hand, to transfer it to Saints or Angels is Sacrilegious and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous, <hi>See thou do it not.</hi> Now what bodily geſtures are appropriate to Divine Worſhip, muſt not be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41255:3"/> from the geſtures themſelves, (for one may fall at the feet of their Superiour without a crime, as <hi>Abigail</hi> did to <hi>David,)</hi> but from the circumſtances of Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary <note place="margin">1 Sam 25. 24.</note> time, place, and matter in hand; as when they are tendred upon an Holy-day, in a Temple or Oratory, and when Religion, Prayer, and Devotion, is the matter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
            <p>But if the Crime the Apoſtle was here incurring, was through miſtake of the perſon, thinking him to be Chriſt; Then it us reads this Lecture, That <hi>bodily adoration in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Right, but miſtaken in the object is yet peccant against the Commandment of Worſhip.</hi> And both theſe would affright a conſiderative mind at the peril of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> where, if the <hi>Hoſt</hi> be not miſtaken, the Senſe of Mankind muſt; and if all the Canoniz'd Saints be truly what they are eſteemed, yet doubtleſs no better than the <hi>Angel</hi> in the Text. Neither will the diſtinction of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſalve the Crime ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in this latter caſe, ſeeing there was no room for it in this of the Apoſtle and the Angel here.</p>
            <p>For why could not this Angel have applied the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to ſalve the breach of the Commandment, as well as the Angelical Doctor can? But that when the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſpeak Religion, there is indeed no diſtinction at all. But 'tis the importance of the laſt words I deſign to conſider,
<q>
                  <hi>For the Teſtimony of Jeſus is the Spirit of Prophecy.</hi>
               </q> Which words are a reaſon, why the <hi>Angel</hi> was the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <hi>fellow Servant, &amp;c.</hi> For whoſoever by the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> revealed the Divine will, was concerned in the common <hi>Testimony of Jeſus;</hi> becauſe all Prophecy (truly ſo called) had <hi>Jeſus</hi> and his <hi>Intereſts</hi> for its grand Subject; therefore whoſoever was employed therein,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41255:3"/> whether Angel to Man, or one Man to another; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before or after the exhibition of Jeſus, were (as to that employment) <hi>fellow Servants,</hi> and had the <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Jeſus:</hi> though ſubpaena'd to it, as <hi>Balaam</hi> was, by that Power that could give the man the Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, as well as his <hi>Aſs</hi> the Gift of Speaking. And ſo <note place="margin">Numb. 24. 2. &amp;c.</note> much may ſerve to account for the words, as they are a reaſon why the Angel was the Apoſtle's fellow Servant, and of Brethren. I ſhall now conſider them as a diſtinct propoſition; <hi>The Teſtimony of Jeſus is the Spirit of Prophecy;</hi> which in logical order is to be placed thus, <hi>The Spirit of Prophecy is the Teſtimony of Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not diſcuſſing the variety either the word <hi>Prophecy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">After Chriſt's Exhibition, the Prophetical light ſhone clearer, even to diſcover the obſcurity of its own former ſhades: ſo that in this illuſtration of the former ancient Prophets, did the latter Spirit of Prophecy very much conſiſt; and hence in Apoſtolical days <hi>to Prophecy,</hi> is to explain the intended or Evangelical meaning of the Old Teſtament. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 13, 19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hence the phraſe, <hi>Liberty of Prophecying, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>Teſtimony</hi> may admit in their ſignifications elſewhere, I ſhall take them here (as I judge they ought to be) in their moſt obvious and primary ſenſe.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Teſtimony</hi> is a declarative proof to make good his cauſe for whom it is produc'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prophecy</hi> moſt properly implies two things; Firſt, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of the Divine will or mind;</hi> and, Secondly, <hi>Prediction;</hi> which latter is annex'd to the former, as a ſign or rational evidence of the Truth and Divinity of the Revelation: For God offers no Revelation to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, but upon grounds of rational ſatisfaction that it is from himſelf, <hi>i. e.</hi> under ſome convictive Characters of <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Prediction</hi> is this Character annex'd to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation as a Seal for humane Satisfaction, that 'tis Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, or from God himſelf. This being a preſumptive Rule with Humane Nature, That <hi>what Gody ſaies is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41255:4"/> indubitably true, and what he commands ought inſtantly to be obeyed:</hi> (And 'tis upon theſe grounds of Natures allowance that all divine Revelation is founded;) But that which convictively proves the <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Revelation</hi> to be Divine, is the determinate prediction of things fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not neceſſary in their cauſes.</p>
            <p>Thus, that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſhould let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go, was the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation; <note place="margin">Exod. 7. 16, 17, 18, &amp;c.</note> and that <hi>Moſes</hi> would at ſuch a time work ſuch a Wonder, was the <hi>Prediction, i. e.</hi> the Sign given to prove the Revelation from God. Therefore his Wonders <note place="margin">1 Kin. 22. 25, 28. 1 Sam. 10. 2, 3, 4, 5, 7.</note> are called <hi>Signs;</hi> not only becauſe Wonders or Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles (for all Prophetical Signs were not ſo,) but becauſe preſignified; and therein, when fulfilled, Significators of Divinity in the Revelation.</p>
            <p>Seeing then, that the Revelation (which I conceive is alwaies a Precept or Prohibition, with Promiſes or Threatnings annext) in its acceptance with men depends upon Prediction, as the Commiſſion doth upon the Seal. <hi>The Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> is moſt properly the <hi>Spirit of Prediction;</hi> or <hi>that Spirit</hi> which can confirm the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation by <hi>foretelling Futurities</hi> of a contingent nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> things only within the ſphere of <hi>Omniſcience.</hi> For I judge the weight of this Text lies here, and not in the abſtract notion of Revelation, as the late <hi>Tract</hi> upon it ſeems to apprehend.</p>
            <p>And this being premiſed for the ſenſe I take the words in, every word in the <hi>Propoſition</hi> ſeems pregnant with a peculiar Obſervation, which I ſhall offer you in theſe Three <hi>Particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Spirit of Prophecy is the <hi>Teſtimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, i. e.</hi> his, and none beſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> 'Tis not the Perſon employed, Man or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, upon whom the validity of this Teſtimony depends; but 'tis, <hi>The Spirit of Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41255:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That primarily and above all others, the Spirit of Prophecy is, <hi>The Teſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This laſt, becauſe little conſidered by any, that I have ſeen, or not ſo much as the Argument in my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion deſerves, is that I mainly intend; and therefore without occurring to all the Objections I foreſee in the two former, I ſhall diſpatch them briefly.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Spirit of Prophecy is the Teſtimony <hi>of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus:</hi> ſo peculiarly his, that it never was produced to abet any cauſe or intereſt, but his, and what related to it.</p>
            <p>The firſt time the Spirit of Prophecy appeared in the World, was in the concerns of Jeſus; to foretel his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and his undertakings. <hi>The Seed of the Woman ſhall break the Serpents head,</hi> Gen. 3. 15.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the Divine Spirit before reduc'd the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into order, when it <hi>moved,</hi> or <hi>brooded</hi> upon the <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 2.</note> face of the Waters, and as that word imports, <hi>hatch'd</hi> the World into a lively form; but this it did as a <hi>Spirit of Power,</hi> not as a <hi>Spirit of Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When it exerted it ſelf as a Spirit of Prophecy, from firſt to laſt it treated ſolely of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and his Intereſts, ſuch as were either antecedently, concomitantly, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently relating to his exhibition and undertakings: as all things relating to his Church in all Ages, or its Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, were; as in <hi>Egypts</hi> caſe, the Nations, the four Monarchies.</p>
            <p>Whether this Spirit ſtept abroad into the Heathen World; as in the <hi>Baalamitick,</hi> and <hi>Sybilline;</hi> or it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd it ſelf, as generally, to the <hi>Patriarchal</hi> and <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiſh</hi> part, as in the <hi>Prophetical Oracles;</hi> its chief Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand was, to give Teſtimony <hi>to Jeſus,</hi> and mentioned other matters (as <hi>Cyrus,</hi> the Nations, the four Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies) for the connexions ſake of him and his Church?</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:41255:5"/>
            <p>The grand Objection that I here foreſee, is that of the <hi>Heathen Divinations,</hi> in matters where <hi>Jeſus</hi> or his Intereſts were unconcerned; but ſure, would the limits of this Diſcourſe permit, they might all be ſhewed to fall much ſhort of the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy.</hi> For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Premonitions by Dreams, either in the firſt Ages or our own, (which I will not abſolutely reject,) I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem no other, than the Preventive acts of a gracious Providence; the like to which may by wiſe men be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in other various Inſtances of common life, which naturally awaken the Mind to caution and reflection; but will not amount to the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy:</hi> or elſe, if ever they aroſe to the dignity of that title, it will be found they were in order to the Teſtimony <hi>of Jeſus;</hi> as <hi>Abimelechs</hi> might be ſhewed to be: for I can never <note place="margin">Gen. 20.</note> think that any other cauſes, beſides what related to him, (as <hi>Sarahs</hi> did) ſhould be vouchſafed the honour of ſo divine a Teſtimony. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 41. 21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Chap. 43. 9. and Chap. 44. 7. 24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Humane prudence may conjecture, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hit it; it cannot <hi>certainly foretel</hi> future Contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies without this Spirit.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Angelical Sagacity may with great proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility foreſee Contingencies near at hand; when once conceived, and animated in the womb of Second cauſes; (as the iſſue of a Battel, or a cauſe depending;) but this preſaging faculty of Angels, whether good or bad, is ever defective in two properties requiſite to the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy.</hi> Firſt, In the <hi>certainty</hi> of their foreſight. Secondly, In the <hi>diſtance</hi> of the things fore-ſeen. For defect in <hi>Certainty,</hi> the moſt renowned Heathen Oracles were generally ambiguous, thereby to ſalve their Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, be the event what it would. And for defect in <hi>Diſtance</hi> they were ſeldom I think, or never conſulted, but about the ſucceſs of a Actions already on the Wheel,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41255:5"/> or prepared for: And I ſuppoſe theſe two Conſiderations may help us to account for all the arts of Heathen Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; for why might not a prudent man, that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the temper and intereſt of both Armies have ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied young <hi>Pompey</hi> the night before the <hi>Pharſalian</hi> field, as well as the Witch of <hi>Theſſaly</hi> by her familiar <hi>Daemon?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lucan.</hi> lib. 6.</note> eſpecially if acquainted with <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Prophecy (as no doubt the Devils were) concerning the <hi>Fourth Monarchy,</hi> which now call'd for its proper head in <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and was inconſiſtent longer under <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Cauſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, How far ſoever into the future the <hi>Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances</hi> of Men or Angels may ſucceed without this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Prophecy, yet in all ſuch matters two things are obſervable: Firſt, That the laſt reſults of ſuch plots and contrivances, proved ever ſomething beſide, if not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, to the grand intendment of the Projector: of which inſtances in all politick Geſts recorded, are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable. Secondly, The moſt projecting Politician, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting from this Spirit, ever found ſome link in the Chain of his Contrivances broken; which he was forced to piece up anew, as the circumſtances of his affairs would permit.</p>
            <p>And to let all men ſee, that only the All-ſeeing Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of God ſhall ſtand, all other Conſults even at their height have fallen, as in the Four Monarchies; whereof the beſt account that can be given is, that the utmoſt created Foreſight is ſhort and defectible, and therefore the beſt laid Projects ſubject to defeat.</p>
            <p>Whereas the unerring <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> is both <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and extended to the moſt <hi>diſtant</hi> futurity: ſo that it has determinately foretold <hi>(ex. gr.)</hi> the riſe and fall of the Four Monarchies, that ſo it might make <note n="*" place="margin">For the Communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the World enjoyed by being under one Monarchy, did extreamly facilitate the Goſpels pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation; and being foretold to be in the Fourth Monarchy, did in all reaſon oblige it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſubmiſſion, as to the Ordinance of Heaven.</note> way for Jeſus and his everlaſting Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41255:6"/>
            <p>Laſtly, (what looks with the face of the moſt difficult Objection,) the Oracles and Divinations of the Heathen; (for I ſhall ſay nothing of our Aſtrological vanity,) were apparently acted by the Sophiſtry of evil, Men or Angels, and were as far below the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> as <hi>Lieger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du-main</hi> is of working of Miracles.</p>
            <p>And that the Prince of Devils, though ſo ambitious to be like God, could never reach the Spirit of Prophecy, this to me is a demonſtration, <hi>viz. That in the daies of his celebrated Oracles (when it was propereſt,) he has not foretold the coming of ſome ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Antichriſtian Power (as</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The boldeſt attempt in a determinate Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction that I remember amongſt the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, is that mentioned by St. <hi>Auſtin, de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> lib 18. cap. 53. <hi>Excogitaverunt neſcio quos verſus Graecos, tanquam conſulenti, cuidam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino Oraculo effuſos, ut Coleretur Chriſti nomen per 365 annos; deinde completo memorato nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero annorum, ſine morâ ſumeret finem.</hi> This, as he in the next Chapter computes, ſhould have been fulfilled in the Conſulſhip of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius</hi> and <hi>Eutychianus.</hi> Whether it was <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum daemonum aut figmentum hominum,</hi> he aſſures us not. To me it ſeems grounded on ſome Opinions of the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, concerning Antichriſt's appearance; but how miſerably it fail'd, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves, that in the very year <hi>Gaudentius</hi> and <hi>Jovius</hi> overthrew the Temples of the Heathen gods in <hi>Cartage; Et plurimi Chriſtiani facti qui tanquam verâ illâ Divinatione revocabantur à fide, poſtquam eam completo eodem annorum nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero inanem irridendamque viderunt.</hi> De Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. lib. 18. cap. 54.</note> 
               <hi>the Papal or Mahometan) under the Character of a divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> For certainly this he would have done, had not the ability of his own Spirit fail'd him, both as to the <hi>certainty</hi> and <hi>distance</hi> of ſuch a contingency; becauſe nothing imaginable could have bruiſed the heel of the Womans <hi>Seed</hi> ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly, confirmed <hi>Gentile</hi> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſtaggar'd the Faith of Mankind ſo effectually as this; by confronting a teſtimony for <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> out of the Heathen Oracles, as good as that for <hi>Chriſt</hi> out of the Old Teſtament Prophecies. And therefore all that the Serpent can do in this matter is, to play the <hi>after-game</hi> as ſubtilly as may be, and inſpire <hi>Mahomet</hi> when he finds him En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſtick and amongſt a People fit for deluſion, and ſo to club to perfect the Impoſture: or elſe, to transform himſelf into an Angel of Light; (the only way to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief the Chriſtian Church) as the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> doth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41255:6"/> himſelf into the <hi>Catholick,</hi> or a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> himſelf, into a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; or a <hi>Quaker</hi> himſelf into a man of Perfection.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I may not ſcan every objected Inſtance in Heathen Divination, I ſhall in general only ſay, that who ſo affirms any other than the <hi>Divine,</hi> can be the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> ſeems to ſuffrage with them that blaſphemed againſt him; in leaving no diſtinctive Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter to diſcern the Holy Spirit by, and ſo may aſcribe to <hi>Beelzebub</hi> what is the <hi>Divine Spirit</hi>'s prerogative: And I call this of Prediction the Divine Spirit's prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, becauſe God in the Prophet puts all other Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners upon this Teſt. <hi>Iſa. 41. 21, &amp;c. Produce your cauſe, ſaith the Lord, Bring forth your strong reaſons, ſaith the King of Jacob. Let them bring them forth, and ſhew us</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>what ſhall happen; let them ſhew the former things what they be, that we may conſider 'em, and know the latter end of them, or declare us things for to come. Shew the things that are to come hereafter, that we may know that ye are gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Allowing then, that the ſphere of <hi>Jeſus</hi>'s Intereſts, is as large as the concerns of his Churches in all Ages; the Prophecies of <hi>Enoch, Noah, Jacob,</hi> and Others, before his Incarnation; or of <hi>Agabus,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> and Others after it, make no Objection againſt this Truth, That the Spirit of Prophecy is the Teſtimony <hi>of Jeſus,</hi> and nones elſe: ſo that no cauſe diſtinct or oppoſite to his can produce it; all divine Revelation centring in him; <hi>to which give all the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 10. 43.</note> 
               <hi>Prophets witneſs:</hi> 'tis thereſore called the <hi>Spirit of Christ in the Prophets, 1 Pet.</hi> 1. 11. and 'tis obſervable, when this Divine Spirit was to convince <hi>the World</hi> of Sin for not believing; it ſilenc'd all the <hi>Oracles</hi> in the World both true and falſe, I mean both <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Heathen,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act, 16. 16, 17. 19. 16, 19.</note> which might be made uſe of in oppoſition to the Goſpel. And that's my firſt Obſervation, 'Tis the Teſtimony <hi>of Jeſus,</hi> i. e. <hi>peculiarly,</hi> and nones elſe.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41255:7"/>
            <p>Secondly, 'Tis not the Perſon employed, Man or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, on whom the validity of this Teſtimony depends: but 'tis <hi>The Spirit of Prophecy:</hi> not only as revealing God's mind; but as predicting to confirm the Revelation; <hi>i. e.</hi> 'tis the Teſtimony of <hi>Omniſcient Veracity,</hi> or of <hi>the prime Verity;</hi> for nothing can furniſh out the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> but a Science, and Truth that is indefectible and infinite. (For the account of <hi>certainty</hi> in the Divine Preſcience, as to Contingencies, and the products of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, muſt not be reſolv'd into the Decree, as if God certainly foreknew this would be the product of Liberty therefore, becauſe he decreed it, for the Decree makes all Contingencies equally poſſible, unleſs we introduce <hi>Fata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> But the certainty of <hi>Preſcience</hi> muſt be reſolved ſolely into the <hi>Infinity of Science. There is no ſearching of his underſtanding. Iſa.</hi> 40. 28.)</p>
            <p>So then, whether it be Man or Angel that's acted by the Spirit of Prophecy; whether <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Balaam, Simeon</hi> or <hi>Caiphas,</hi> it matters not! (contrary to <hi>Maimonides</hi>'s Rules about Qualifications,) the Teſtimony is the <hi>Spirits of Prophecy,</hi> the atteſtation to the Revelation is made by the <hi>Prime Verity,</hi> and the force lies in the preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptive truth of Nature's conceſſion. <hi>What God ſays is true,</hi> or as St. <hi>John</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>If we receive the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of men, the witneſs of God is greater. 1 Joh.</hi> 5. 9.</p>
            <p>For all things in the World are true, or falſe, as they have, or want the Teſtimony of the <note n="*" place="margin">Thus the Sun evidenceth it ſelf by its own light; and all other things viſible, by that illuſtration of Light it lends them, either tranſiently as to the Air, or permanently as to ſome Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Prime Verity;</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that <hi>Verity</hi> record its Teſtimony in the ſettled Laws and Volumes of Nature; upon which the ſtudy of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy and all Secular knowledge depends: or in the preſcripts of Revelation, called for diſtinctions ſake <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural knowledge,</hi> i. e. <hi>therefore</hi> this or that Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is <hi>true</hi> in the nature of things, <hi>becauſe</hi> their cauſes and effects are apprehended as the firſt Cauſe, and the Divine Truth did conſtitute them. And ſo in <hi>Revelation:</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41255:7"/> this or that created Knowledge and Judgment is <hi>true,</hi> or <hi>falſe,</hi> which apprehends it according to the word and meaning of the firſt Revealer, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>We ſee this in Humane affairs, where the grand deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Truth depends entirely upon an <hi>Oath;</hi> and <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> upon an Oath, <hi>becauſe an Oath is the atteſtation, or appeal to the Prime Verity;</hi> which Teſtimony upon Oath being ever eſteemed moſt Sacred (till the Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Atheiſtical prophaneneſs of our Swearing Age eſſayed to unhallow, and make it common,) <hi>Therefore</hi> it muſt follow, <hi>That whatever is atteſted by the Prime Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity itſelf,</hi> is <hi>true</hi> without any other, or againſt any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrary Evidence, (and 'tis this that renders the Faith of Chriſtian Myſteries reaſonable.) Now the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations or Revelations of the Spirit of Prophecy, Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evidently appear to proceed from the <hi>Prime Verity,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no knowledge but the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Infinite,</hi> can reach the Spirit of Prophecy, <hi>i. e.</hi> can confirm Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by certain Prediction.</p>
            <p>And if I miſtake not, this wounds the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> who has taken his paſtime in theſe waters of the Sanctuary, and may ſhew him that Divine Faith may, and ought to be reſolved into <hi>Divine Truth,</hi> that ſo its certainty might be ſtedfaſt, as any knowledge in the World; for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may <hi>miniſter</hi> to this Faith, its relyance muſt be upon <hi>Divinity</hi> itſelf: and happy were it, would men conſider the grounds of their Faith, that they might with the Apoſtle amidſt all the oppoſitions of the World ſtand firm, with a <hi>Nevertheleſs I am not aſhamed, for I</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 12.</note> 
               <hi>know whom I have believed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that Mankind might have rational and ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grounds for Faith in Jeſus. The <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> which ever gave Teſtimony to him, exerted it ſelf both as a Spirit of Omnipotency (in <hi>Miracles,)</hi> and of Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (in <hi>Prophecy,)</hi> to the end Men might believe the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41255:8"/> great concerns of Revelation, upon the <hi>demonſtrative</hi> grounds of <hi>Divine perfection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I take to be St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s meaning, when he ſays, <hi>My preaching was not with enticing words of man's</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor 2. v. 4,</note> 
               <hi>wiſdom, but in Demonſtration of the Spirit, and of power, i. e.</hi> of Miracles wrought by the <hi>Spirit of Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency,</hi> and of <hi>Demonſtrative</hi> conviction out of the Prophets, who appear to have been acted by the <hi>Spirit of Omniſcience</hi> and <hi>Truth itſelf,</hi> by the Events anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Predictions: <hi>That your Faith</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>ſhould</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> 
               <hi>not ſtand in the wiſdom of men,</hi> (either the Authority of the <hi>Civil State,</hi> with the <hi>Leviathan;</hi> or ſtrong <hi>Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> with Others:) <hi>but in the Power of God, i. e.</hi> in <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, v. 4.</note> the <hi>Divinity</hi> itſelf; which, when it gives Teſtimony, Natural light unqueſtionably concludes it <hi>true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if it be demanded, which way the Apoſtle made his <hi>Demonſtrations in the Spirit,</hi> I ſuppoſe he tells us, v. 13. <hi>We ſpeak not in the words which man's wiſdom teacheth (i. e.</hi> according to the ſtudied Rules of Arts now in <hi>Greece,) but which the Holy Ghoſt teacheth, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring ſpiritual things with ſpiritual, (i. e.</hi> comparing the Doctrine and Tranſactions of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> with the Prophecies of the <hi>Old:)</hi> and hereby the Faith of Jeſus is <hi>Demonſtrated</hi> to be Divine, becauſe atteſted by the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> for in the <hi>9th</hi> verſe he had quoted the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> and ſo in all his preaching (as <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 2, 3. and for ſtudying this <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> or comparing the New Teſtament with the Old, the <hi>Bere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> are ſo much commended, <hi>v.</hi> 11.) and nothing is plainer, than that all the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and even <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf did thus argue or convince out of the Old Teſtament Prophets: The force therefore of the Teſtimony depends ſolely upon the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy:</hi> or that 'tis the Teſtimony of the <hi>Prime</hi> and <hi>Omniſcient Verity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:41255:8"/>
            <p>I muſt not ſtay to clear my hand of the <hi>Tractatus Theologico-politicus,</hi> who has reſolv'd the <hi>Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> not as St. <hi>Peter</hi> did, into being <hi>Moved by the Holy Ghoſt, 2 Pet, 1. 21.</hi> but into the <hi>Craſis</hi> of the Imaginative <hi>faculty;</hi> that ſo you may know him the Firſt-born of the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and by their <hi>Hypotheſes,</hi> whoſe Scholars <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tract.</hi> p. 7, &amp;c.</note> both were, even his who reſolv'd the Creation of the Univerſe into the fortuitous concurs of Atoms.</p>
            <p>Neither may I reflect upon that <hi>Moral Probability,</hi> which ſome ſeem to think a ſufficient foundation for Faith, further than to ſay, <hi>That matters reveal'd and confirm'd by the Spirit of Prophecy, are, and ought to be (ſo far as reveal'd) as certain Truths, as any Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations in the World beſides.</hi> I fear not after St. <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay, that matters of a Moral and Spiritual nature may be <hi>demonſtrated:</hi> taking <hi>Demonſtration</hi> not in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd ſignification which the School of <hi>Heathen Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> affixt to it; but in the reality of the thing, and with reſpect to the end for which <hi>Demonſtration</hi> ſerves, <hi>viz.</hi> a Proof that creates a knowledge certain and indubitable; and this the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> not as revealing, but as confirming Revelation by <hi>Prediction,</hi> doth. Which brings me to the Third and chief deſign'd Particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That of all other Teſtimonies of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Spirit of Prophecy is <hi>The Testimony.</hi> My meaning is,</p>
            <p>There is no ſuch ſtanding, ſatisfactory, and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative proof of the Divinity of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi>'s <hi>Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Faith</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as the Spirit of Prophecy is.</p>
            <p>There are indeed many other Teſtimonies of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> better than moſt, or any other cauſe beſide his, can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of Angels, both good and bad! the <hi>good</hi> in obſequious attendancies upon his Birth, his <note place="margin">Luke 2. 13. 22. 43, &amp;c.</note> Agonies, his Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion. The <hi>bad,</hi> in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41255:9"/> flying Fears, concluding, at leaſt ſtrongly ſuſpecting, by <note place="margin">Luke 8. 28. Mark 1. 24.</note> the <hi>Predictions</hi> of the Old Prophets, who it was they now had to deal with in Humane Nature; even <hi>the Holy One of God,</hi> or the <hi>Seed promiſed</hi> to break the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi>'s head.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of Men, both his Friends, and Enemies. His <hi>Friends</hi> extol, adore him, die for him: his <hi>Enemies</hi> of all ſorts confeſs him an extraordinary Perſon, though a deceiver: as <hi>Celſus, Jalian, Mahomed,</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> the <hi>Apostate,</hi> the <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> the <hi>Infidel: Mahomed</hi> is kindeſt of all the reſt, for he will allow him to be his <hi>Pew-fellow</hi> in Prophecy, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition he may but ſit above him. Nay,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There are more venerable Witneſſes, than either <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Men,</hi> I mean thoſe <hi>Three in Heaven,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 5. 7, 8.</note> and thoſe <hi>Three on Earth;</hi> where, though the Divine Spirit make One in either Three, yet (which I wonder is no more obſerved and inſiſted on) the <hi>Spirit</hi> as 'tis in this ſence explain'd, <hi>The Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> is (however to my apprehenſion) <hi>The Testimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not in preference to the Others conſider'd in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but conſider'd with reference to Mankind, who are to be Judges of their Evidence; and whoſe Judging faculties are more ſuſceptive of ſatisfaction from <hi>the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> as a <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> or infinite <hi>Science</hi> in <hi>truth;</hi> than from the ſame Spirit in any other way of Evidence: the reaſon of which I conceive to be this, That the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in the way of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> or in the diſplay of <hi>Omniſcience,</hi> is more directly accommodate to humane Intellect, our faculty of Science, than any other operation of the Spirit is. For the ſtrongeſt tendencies of Intellect are to the Science of Truth; and therefore acts of Omniſcient Truth, are more accommodate to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane underſtanding, than acts of Power, Wiſdom being that it is more delighted in, than Strength.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41255:9"/>
            <p>If any Revelation be from God, by the foreſaid Rule of Natural knowledge, it ought to be accepted and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to. But whether that which pretends Revelation, be from God, or no; is the only Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Now the Argument from <hi>Miracles</hi> is preſt by all, this of <hi>Prediction</hi> by few or none; but without depreciating the former, I muſt confeſs ever ſince I conſider'd it, the latter is weightier and more convictive with me: for I am more fully ſatisfied, That the whole Series of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <hi>Revelation</hi> is Divine, becauſe I find all along, the Spirit of <hi>Prediction</hi> interwoven; than becauſe I read ſuch and ſuch Miracles done. For I find the <hi>Alcharon</hi> pretending Miracles, but not daring to pretend Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. So that of all the innate Characters of Divinity pretended to in any written Law, this of <hi>Prediction</hi> is peculiar to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>This therefore is the Propoſition I ſhall inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Spirit of Prophecy, not</hi> as revealing God's mind only (for that's the Queſtion,) <hi>but</hi> as predicting to confirm what is revealed, is primarily <hi>The Teſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reaſons I ſhall at preſent offer are theſe Two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe this <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> is that Tally cannot be counterfeited, but may eaſily be diſcovered by certain Rules of tryal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe all Ages are equally under its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, which they are not as to any other Teſtimony abſtracting from this; nay, ſucceeding Ages have the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in this, and may rely upon it as that which gives credit to all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> is that Tally cannot be counterfeited, but may eaſily be diſcovered; and therefore God gave it to the World to prevent delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in matters of Revelation.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:41255:10"/>
            <p>The intentions of his Mercy to recover Mankind from the Fall, God held forth the faith and hope of, to <hi>Adam</hi> and all his Poſterity, in the Promiſe of a <hi>Seed</hi> that ſhould <hi>break the Serpent's head, i. e.</hi> in the Goſpel ſtyle, ſhould <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15. 1 Joh. 3. 8.</note> 
               <hi>deſtroy the works of the Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leſt the ſubtil <hi>Serpent</hi> ſhould ſet up one of his own party, under the ſpecious pretences of <hi>redeeming</hi> Mankind, when the conceal'd intention was to <hi>enſlave</hi> them more, God did by the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ages ſo individualize that Redeemer, ſo preciſely foretel his Time, ſo notifie all his Tranſactions, that in common reaſon he might be known from all others; and this want of reaſon is that our Saviour wonders at in the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who ſought a <hi>Sign</hi> of him! <hi>Ye can diſcern the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 16. 1.</note> 
               <hi>face of the sky, but can ye not diſcern the ſigns of the times? i. e.</hi> that theſe are the Times of your expected <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> preſignified by the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> in the Old Teſtament? and that ye need no Sign from me to prove it, but the correſpondency of my time and actions to their Predictions.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> had thus characteriz'd the Perſon, the Time, the Actions, and Sufferings of the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> that this <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> muſt needs be him of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> did write, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 45. I ſhall not go about to clear! In this I refer to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, eſpecially St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> who ſtill appeals, <note n="*" place="margin">As <hi>Matt.</hi> 18. 17. and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</note> even in Chriſt's <hi>Miracles,</hi> to what was written in the Prophets.</p>
            <p>Taking then this for granted; I ſay, that this <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> was that Tally could not be counterfeited, given therefore by God to prevent deluſion in matters pretending to Revelation, and ſo 'tis emphatically, <hi>The Teſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that a lying Spirit could not pretend a <hi>Divination,</hi> as well as a <hi>Revelation;</hi> but that it could not predict a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41255:10"/> future contingent Event, eſpecially remote, ſo as to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture on the tryal of Prophecy; and all <hi>Heathen Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination</hi> boggled here.</p>
            <p>For 'tis as infallible a Rule, <hi>That none but the Divine Spirit can be the Spirit of Prophecy:</hi> as 'tis, <hi>That remote future contingencies can be clearly foreſeen, and certainly foretold by none, but Omniſcient Veracity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore ſetting aſide the Works of Creation, which found Natural Religion; there's no effect that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues an immediate Divinity for its cauſe ſo clearly, as the Prophetical Predictions do; becauſe there are more eaſie and certain <hi>Rules of Tryal</hi> to diſcern which is the true Spirit of Prophecy, than any Divine operation after the creation of things.</p>
            <p>For wonderful Works may be ſaid to be the products of that energy, which the Creator at firſt enricht Nature with, and ſo a <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quare abſolutè concludimus, omnia quae in Scripturis Verè narrantur contigiſſe, ea ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum leges Naturae, ut omnia neceſſario conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſſe. Et ſi quid reperiatur legibus Naturae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnare, aut ex iis conſequi non potuiſſe; planè credendum id à Sacrilegis hominibus ſacris Literis adjectum eſſe.</hi> Tract. <hi>Theo. pol.</hi> c. 6. p 71.</note> late Off-ſpring of the <hi>Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> affirms. But <hi>Prediction</hi> is Self-evidently an immediate iſſue from the Divinity, <hi>de novo;</hi> which if ſo, and preſt home upon the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan</hi> and his Firſt-born now mentioned, will ſhew them other grounds for Chriſtian Faith, and Scriptures, than only the <hi>Authority of God's</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Leviath.</hi> cap. 36, 37.</note> 
               <hi>Lieutenants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Rules to try the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> by, as I take it, are but theſe Two.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the thing pretended to be a Revelation from God, (which was alwaies an Injuction or Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition with their annexes) had no intrinſecal Evil in it, or neceſſarily derivative from it, peccant againſt the Laws of <hi>Morality,</hi> ſettled in the firſt Creation, <hi>(i. e.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Natural Religion, or a former Law reveal'd, and on good grounds accepted as <hi>Divine;)</hi> for God's Laws never contradict one another; neither is his Wiſdom ſo ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41255:11"/> as to ſet up contrary Inſtitutions of life: and therefore the Chriſtian Law <hi>deſtroys not</hi> the <hi>Moſaical,</hi> but compleats its imperfections; <hi>I came not to deſtroy, but to fulfil, i. e.</hi> to fill up. This is the primary and grand Rule of Tryal: To which mens non-attendance, has at laſt debaucht all Religion, made it a wild and unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thing, and let in that Spirit of Giddineſs, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes men to <hi>every wind of Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Rule of Tryal is this, That the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion pretending from God, and not peccant, as aforeſaid, ſhould be confirm'd with a Sign, <hi>i. e. Prediction fulfill'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two Rules brought the whole <hi>Spirit of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> under trial; let the <hi>Rabbies,</hi> and they that in this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire them, multiply never ſo many, I apprehend not that the Scriptures have given us any more, or that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon requires them.</p>
            <p>Only Two things are here to be obſerv'd: Firſt, That in whatever matter it conſiſted, whether <hi>Miracle,</hi> or not; yet being a contingency, the <hi>formality</hi> of a Sign conſiſted in <hi>Prediction fulfill'd.</hi> Secondly, That the Rule of Tryal by Signs, was but <hi>Secondary,</hi> and ſubordinate to that of tryal by Natural Religion, <hi>i. e.</hi> a former Law, whether that of <hi>Creation</hi> or <hi>Revelation</hi> after, confirmed and accepted. And all this is plain from <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. and the <hi>13th</hi> Chapters.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>When a Prophet ſpeaketh in the Name of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chap. 18. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, (i. e.</hi> pretends a Revelation,) <hi>if the thing follow not, nor come to paſs; that is the thing which the Lord hath not ſpoken.</hi> The defect of <hi>Prediction fulfill'd</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws the pretences of <hi>Inſpiration,</hi> or <hi>Revelation;</hi> which neceſſarily argues whatever the materiality of a Sign be, its <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 28. 9. Ezek. 33. 33.</note> 
               <hi>formality</hi> conſiſts in <hi>Prediction fulfill'd:</hi> Though I allow 'twas often (but not alwaies) in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or work miraculous, that what <hi>Omniſcience</hi> had ſaid, <hi>Omnipotence</hi> might back; and awaken the Underſtanding by the impreſſions on ſenſe.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41255:11"/>
            <p>Secondly, If a <hi>Sign</hi> or <hi>Prediction</hi> ſhould be fulfill'd, to promote Idolatry, or any thing deſtructive to Natural Religion, or a former Divine Law reveal'd, <hi>Thou ſhalt not hearken to the voice of that Prophet, for the Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 3, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>your God proveth you.</hi> The meaning is, In matters of <hi>Immorality,</hi> the Caſe is not to be try'd by the Rule of Signs, but by the primary Rule, that of a former Law, whether in Creation, which we call <hi>Natural Religion,</hi> or in ſome well-grounded former Revelation, as this of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>'s was in reſpect of all following Prophets; and ſo the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in reſpect of all New light, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For whatever has any intrinſecal Evil neceſſarily adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, or repugnant to a former Law ſurely believ'd to be Divine; whatever overthrows <hi>Humanity,</hi> the natural Notions of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil, Truth</hi> and <hi>Falſhood;</hi> which is Natural Religion, or the Law of Creation, (upon whoſe bottoms all Supernatural ſtands,) let it pretend <hi>Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme</hi> and <hi>Infallibility</hi> on the one hand, or <hi>Spiritual giftedneſs</hi> and <hi>Inſpiration</hi> on the other, 'tis certainly, not Divine, but Diabolical, though ſtrengthned with Signs and Wonders. And 'tis then men are given up to ſtrong deluſions to <hi>believe Lies,</hi> when through pretences of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration they have not received the <hi>love</hi> of this Truth, but let go this grand and primary Rule of <hi>Tryal;</hi> for doubtleſs, were the pretences of new Revelations and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations examin'd cloſely by this Rule, and obſerv'd how they overthrow Natural Religion, or the plain Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xims and Duties of Chriſtians; it would diſcover the Impoſtures of <hi>Popery, Fanaticiſm, Mahometiſm,</hi> as well as <hi>Gentiliſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what pretends to Prophetical Revelation, or to be God's Will; being not peccant againſt this firſt Rule; and is <hi>confirm'd with Signs,</hi> or <hi>Prediction fulfill'd;</hi> muſt be allowed to be Divine, as having the <hi>Seal of God</hi> annext, and no mark left to diſcern the counterfeit by; which is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41255:12"/> a caſe <hi>Omnipotent</hi> and <hi>Omniſcient Truth</hi> is concern'd to <note place="margin">Iſai. 44. 25, &amp;c.</note> look to.</p>
            <p>It will perhaps be demanded, if this be ſo. How could the ſeveral Ages of the World make Tryal of the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> in its Teſtimony to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſeeing they liv'd not to ſee the predicted Signs fulfilled?</p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, They liv'd to ſee and know o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Signs or Predictions fulfill'd, which the ſame <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> in connexion to the Teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> had foretold; and that was ſufficient. <hi>Ex. gr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Deluge</hi> was ſign ſufficient to <hi>Noah</hi> and all his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity till <hi>Abraham</hi>'s daies: <hi>Iſaak</hi>'s Birth was ſo to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bondage and Delivery preciſely foretold to <hi>Abraham,</hi> was ſo to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and his Poſterity, till <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets aroſe, and then there wanted none till <hi>Christ</hi>'s time, as might be eaſily ſhew'd.</p>
            <p>So that in every Age God ſubmitted to Tryal that <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> that gave Teſtimony to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> by ſuch Events or Predictions fulfill'd, as peculiarly concern'd the ſight or experienc'd knowledge of thoſe Ages: <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nam quae melior &amp; validior ratio de rebus talibus redditur, quàm cum Omnipotens ea fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere perhibetur, &amp;</hi> Facturu; <hi>dicitur; quae praenunciaſſe</hi> Ibi <hi>legitur,</hi> Ubi <hi>alia multa prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuncia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it, quae</hi> Feciſſe <hi>monſtratu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>?</hi> Aug <hi>de Civit.</hi> lib. 21. cap. 7.</note> and from hence 'twas reaſonable they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That the <hi>ſame Spirit</hi> would not miſcarry in its Teſtimony to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> or the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> promiſed, and ſo particularly decipher'd. And this was the foundation of <hi>Patriarchal Religion,</hi> ſo far as 'twas Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, <hi>i. e.</hi> of <hi>their</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10, 11, 12. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, v. 10. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. v. 11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. v. 12. where <hi>Prediction</hi> and <hi>Revelation</hi> are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht in the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy;</hi> for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation was, <hi>v.</hi> 12 in the <hi>things they mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred,</hi> (or the <hi>ſame Goſpel</hi> to us and them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 2.) the prediction was, in <hi>teſtifying beforehand,</hi> v. 11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Faith,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>From all which I hope I may conclude, that the <hi>Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> in this ſence, is <hi>THE Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Jeſus;</hi> as being that Tally could not be counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited (like the <hi>Roman Ancile</hi> by <hi>Mamurrius)</hi> without
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41255:12"/> diſcovery by the eaſie Rules of Tryal: whereas to me all the other Teſtimonies without this ſeem liable to it.</p>
            <p>And I am perſwaded my freedom in ſaying ſo will not be eſteemed impious by him, that conſiders St. <hi>Peter</hi> has ſaid as much before me, who recognizing the Father's Voice, which he himſelf heard on the Holy Mountain, yet immediately ſubjoyns, <hi>We have alſo a more ſure word</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 18. 19.</note> 
               <hi>of Prophecy; i. e.</hi> more ſure than a Voice from Heaven.</p>
            <p>For the queſtion is not, which is ſurer in itſelf; the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Voice</hi> on Mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> or the <hi>Spirits of Prophecy</hi> in the <hi>Scripture?</hi> but, which is ſurer unto us in the way of our diſcerning? The one I conceive cannot be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited without diſcovery, but may not the other? for a Voice in the Air from a good Angel has been heard, why then not from a bad one? We have no Rules of Tryal, that I know of, for the one; as I have ſhew'd we have for the other; therefore that other is <hi>ſurer to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to evidence this further, 'tis obſervable, That the Father witneſſing refers to the Son; <hi>hear him:</hi> and the <note place="margin">Matt. 17. 5. Joh. 5. 39.</note> Son witneſſing refers to the Spirit of Prophecy; <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>They are they that teſtifie of me;</hi> which is as much as I affirm from the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Text, the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> is eminently <hi>The Teſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that of the <hi>Three</hi> that bear record in Heaven; <hi>to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> is the Teſt of the others, as being that which cannot be counterfeited, but may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by the eaſie Rules of Tryal.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe <hi>Three</hi> on Earth, <hi>the Spirit, the Water,</hi> and <hi>the Blood, i. e.</hi> as they are generally interpreted, Chriſt's Miracles wrought by the <hi>Spirit of Power;</hi> his Holineſs and Purity denoted by the <hi>Water;</hi> and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy to death imply'd by the <hi>Blood:</hi> It may well be ſcrupled, whether they may not all be ſo far counterfeited,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41255:13"/> that without other Conſiderations, they may not alwaies by us be diſcerned, whether they atteſt a Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or Impoſture.</p>
            <p>For Firſt, <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Purity</hi> is a garb Hypocrites may put on ſo artificially, that it may not be in our power to detect it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Conſtancy to death,</hi> is but what a ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion may animate a man to; if it be but of the right <hi>Roman</hi> temper, and <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> mettal; which the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of our Age ſurely have evinc'd.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Spirit of Power,</hi> i. e. <hi>Miracles,</hi> though I grant a <hi>divine Teſtimony</hi> in itſelf, yet may not alwaies be ſo to us; becauſe not ſubjected to ſuch eaſie Rules of Tryal, as the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> is. For how far ſenſible Nature may be under the power of Art, or the Agency of evil Spirits; who is ſo skilful as to determine, the moſt that may be, and the leaſt that is? So that a Beholder may be at a loſs, betwixt a true Miracle, and a lying Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and not know who to believe, <hi>Moſes,</hi> or the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> till one Party quits the field, and confeſs the <hi>Finger of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſenſible, the Common Opinion preſſes me moſt with this Objection, as if my Doctrine evacuated the conviction of our Saviour's <hi>Miracles,</hi> and patroniz'd the <hi>Jews Infidelity,</hi> in not believing for the Works ſake.</p>
            <p>But, as has been obſerv'd by a Judicious Man, this is a <note place="margin">Dr. Jackſon.</note> miſtake, for the <hi>Jews</hi> had a certain Rule of Tryal, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to diſcern that the Works of Jeſus were wrought in <hi>God,</hi> and not in <hi>Beelzebub;</hi> and that <hi>Rule</hi> was no other than the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> which (like the Light) as it Self-evidently manifeſts its own Divinity; ſo by its Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration it manifeſts other things: which <hi>Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> in the Old Teſtament (thoſe Oracles committed to the <hi>Jews)</hi> had foretold that the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> ſo born, ſo <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 2.</note> qualified, ſo circumſtantiated as <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and none other
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41255:13"/> ever was, ſhould do theſe particular Works of wonder. So that the Miracles of Chriſt were to them truly <hi>Signs,</hi> and therefore convictive; not ſolely becauſe Divine ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, (for that was the queſtion,) but becauſe they were Contingencies determinately foretold.</p>
            <p>And this is plain from our Saviour's Anſwer to the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> requiring a Sign, <hi>Matt. 16. 3. Can ye not diſcern the ſigns of the times?</hi> or as St. <hi>Luke, This time,</hi> Chap. 12. 56. where in St. <hi>Luke</hi> Chriſt adds, as awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening their Common reaſon; <hi>Yea, why do you not of your ſelves judge what is right?</hi> which argues that they had a Rule to judge by, <hi>i. e.</hi> why do ye not of your ſelves, without my granting your requeſt of a <hi>Sign;</hi> judge out of the Prophets that I am the <hi>Meſſiah? The works that I do in my Father's Name-bear witneſs of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 5. 36.</note> 
               <hi>me, i. e.</hi> who I am. Why, how? the Anſwer <hi>Chriſt</hi> made to <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> Diſciples, <hi>Matt.</hi> 11. 4. reſolves it, <hi>Go tell John what ye ſee and hear, the blind ſee, the lame walk, &amp;c. i. e.</hi> Go tell him that <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Prophecy you ſee is <note place="margin">ALL <hi>Christ</hi>'s Miracles were Signs to the <hi>Jews,</hi> becauſe preſignified by the Prophets whom the <hi>Jews</hi> believed; and in the Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy of Grace, the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was <hi>therefore</hi> ſent to that People firſt, who had the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy; I am not ſent but to the loſt ſheep of the Houſe of Iſrael:</hi> Why? Mankind had as much intereſt in him as they; but the moſt ſatisfactory, convictive way of propagating his <hi>Faith</hi> to Mankind, was <hi>from them;</hi> which is the reaſon it was to be preach'd to all Nations, <hi>Beginning from Jeruſalem,</hi> Luke 24. 46.</note> fulfilled by me, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 35. 6. and 61. 1. and then let him and you conſider, who I am. Where Chriſt to that grand Queſtion, which was the <hi>Phariſees</hi> as well as <hi>John</hi>'s, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer produceth the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy;</hi> and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he proved his works to be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, or that he was ſent by the <hi>Father,</hi> as he himſelf ſpeaks; and then I allow moſt unqueſtionable and demonſtrative Convictions. And why was not this that which aggran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diz'd their Sin into <hi>blaſphemy</hi> againſt the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Matt.</hi> 12.? that they wilfully withſtood the Convictions, not only of the <hi>Spirit of Power,</hi> but of <hi>Prophecy</hi> too,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41255:14"/> of which latter, they were ſuch competent Judges, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were of the former.</p>
            <p>Nay, 'tis further obſervable in this matter, that after Jeſus had preſt the <hi>Jews</hi> with the <hi>two</hi> firſt Witneſſes in Heaven, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Father's Voice</hi> and the <hi>Son's Miracles. Joh.</hi> 5. 36, 37. he finally laies the ſtreſs of his Convictions on the Writings of the Prophets; <hi>Had ye believed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ye would have believed me, for he wrote of me, i. e.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 5. 46,</note> the grand Witneſs I appeal to at the bar of mens Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is the Spirit of Prophecy in the <hi>written Records, Search the Scriptures:</hi> and all this to prove what Chriſt <note place="margin">v. 39,</note> had ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 30. that the <hi>Father ſent him.</hi> Where, after all the other Teſtimonies produc'd, he finally relies upon the Spirit of Prophecy; <hi>But if ye believe not his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, how ſhall ye believe my words:</hi> where Jeſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <note place="margin">v. 47.</note> plainly acknowledgeth, That in humane Judgment the teſt both of his Words and Works, and all his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions of Divine miſſion (mentioned <hi>v. 30, &amp;c.)</hi> was the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> as predicting.</p>
            <p>So that I ſee not but we may conclude without any derogation, That Chriſt's Miracles receiv'd the force of their conviction from the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> not of <hi>Power</hi> only: and ſo the Apoſtles Miracles did too; for as Chriſt's Miracles were determinately <hi>foretold</hi> by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the Prophets, ſo the Apoſtles Miracles were by Chriſt. Both were Signs, <hi>i. e.</hi> foretold Chriſt's Works in all the Old Teſtament; the Apoſtles, <hi>Mark 16. 17. Theſe Signs ſhall follow them;</hi> and elſewhere.</p>
            <p>And this was the Goſpels <hi>Confirmation, God bearing them witneſs both with Signs and Wonders, and divers</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Miracles, and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> The firſt of <hi>Signs,</hi> convictive, as being the Teſtimony of <hi>Omniſcient Verity;</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Miracles,</hi> awakening the Senſes (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Underſtanding) to conſider that Conviction, as the force of <hi>Omnipotence</hi> moſt effectually in this dull
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41255:14"/> ſtate can: the laſt, of <hi>Gifts,</hi> as qualifying the Goſpels Miniſters to ſo difficult an employment.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, After all their Miracles, both <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and his Apoſtles back their Doctrine with this Teſtimony of the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> and hang the weight of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions thereon; <hi>This is that which was ſpoken,</hi> or <hi>thus it is written,</hi> throughout all the New Teſtament. And I think 'tis moſt remarkable, That after all poſſible ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction given to their Senſes, Chriſt proves the truth of his <hi>Reſurrection</hi> from this Teſtimony; and 'tis ſpoken <hi>ſignanter. Then opened he their understandings, that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 24. 45, 46.</note> 
               <hi>they might underſtand the Scriptures (i. e.</hi> he explain'd the Scriptures intelligibly to them,) <hi>and ſaid unto them, Thus it is written, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all which conſider'd I may conclude this firſt Reaſon, why the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> is <hi>The Teſtimony,</hi> becauſe 'twas that Tally could not be counterfeited, (given therefore to prevent deluſions) for the Rules of Tryal were eaſie and certain: and no Divination could bear the teſt, but what had the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> its Author, or elſe deſerv'd not the name of <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, 'Tis <hi>The Teſtimony,</hi> becauſe all Ages are under its conviction equally, more than they are of any others, abſtracting from this. And my reaſon is, becauſe this Teſtimony is <hi>permanent,</hi> and the reſt, without this, are <hi>tranſient;</hi> though this adjoyned makes even them permanent too. <hi>Ex. gr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Father's Voice</hi> (as I remember) was only heard at the Baptiſm, and Transfiguration of <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Word</hi> incarnate was perſonally preſent, only in the Daies of <hi>Augustus</hi> and <hi>Tiberius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Holy Ghoſt's <hi>Viſible deſcent</hi> was but once at <hi>Jordan,</hi> and once at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Day of <hi>Pentecoſt.</hi> And theſe (as generally interpreted) are the <hi>Three in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41255:15"/> Heaven.</hi> So likewiſe for the other <hi>Three on Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Holineſs</hi> or <hi>Moral goodneſs</hi> is the pretence of every <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> a ſtanding and laudable Teſtimony I confeſs; and therefore the grand deſign of <hi>Jeſus</hi> was to reſtore it effectually, which he did by Supernatural helps, whereas others eſſay'd it by the ſtrength of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alone, which after the <hi>Fall</hi> was impoſſible: ſo that though <hi>Jeſus</hi> in this ſurpaſt all Mankind, yet ſome Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals have been ſet up againſt him, as <hi>Apollonius</hi> by <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To be a <hi>Martyr for a Lie,</hi> when a man believes it, (as the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>ſome ſhall,)</hi> is neither unuſual, nor <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2. 11.</note> unreaſonable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Age of Miracles</hi> (excepting the wiſdom and conduct of <hi>Providence,</hi> which is not regarded) is worn out, for all the <hi>Legendary</hi> Impoſtures of that Church that ſtill pretends them.</p>
            <p>But that which ſtrengthens all the reſt by its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion with them, <hi>The Testimony of the Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> ſtands like a fixed Star, to give light to every hour of time; call'd therefore <hi>The more ſure Word,</hi> and <hi>the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 19. 1 Pet. 1. 25. Not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Word of God which abideth for ever, to which we do well, if we give heed.</hi> My meaning is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Old and New Testaments are standing Witneſſes to our Faith in Jeſus, all Ages may conſult theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, and find the Teſtimony of the</hi> Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy <hi>ſo interwoven in every part, that it certainly evidenceth their Divinity and Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can any other Writing be produc'd, that durſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to foretel ſuch things, and at ſuch a diſtance, to confirm any other pretended Revelation, or Inſtitution contradictory to this? or doth not every Event in theſe anſwer its prediction? <hi>Ex. gr.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41255:15"/>
            <p>Is not the diſperſt condition of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, a <note n="*" place="margin">On thoſe words, <hi>Pſal. 59. 11. Slay them not, leſt my People forget. Scatter them by thy power.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> applying <hi>Them</hi> to the <hi>Jews,</hi> has this excellent remark, <hi>Ne obliti legem Dei, ad hoc de quo agimus teſtimonium, nihil valerent, quoniam ſi cum teſtimonio ſcriptura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in ſuâ tantummodo terrâ, non ubique eſſent; profecto Eccleſia quae ubique est, eos, Prophetia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quae de Chriſto pramiſſae ſunt, teſtes in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus gentibus non haberet. De Civit.</hi> lib. 18. cap. 46. And then concludes, <hi>Ideo nihil eſt firmius ad convincendos quoſlibet alienos, ſi de hac re contenderint: noſtroſque fulciendos, ſi</hi> rectè ſapuerint, <hi>quam ut Divina praedicla de Chriſto, ea proferantur, quae in</hi> Judaeorum <hi>ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pta ſunt Codicibus,</hi> Quibus avulſis de ſedibus proptils, &amp; propter hoc Teſtimonium toto Orbe diſperſis, <hi>Christi uſquequaque crevit Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia.</hi> Ibid. cap. 47.</note> 
               <hi>ſtanding Sign</hi> to all Ages of the World ſince the Goſpels pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation, and a <hi>permanent</hi> Rule of Tryal laid before all conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive men, that both <hi>Teſtaments</hi> which foretold it, proceeded from the unerring Spirit of <hi>Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</hi> Or was there ever any pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel Caſe to theirs? to continue ſo many hundred years without any <hi>Ty</hi> of National Government, and yet not to be loſt in the crowd of the Nations where ſo many muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have happen'd, nor at all (like the <hi>Ten Tribes)</hi> ſwallow'd up in their Diſperſions as wide as the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>I muſt not inſiſt upon other permanent Signs confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptural Revelation, as the Caſe of the <hi>Four Monarchies,</hi> the <hi>Converſion of the Gentiles,</hi> and many more foretold in the Old and New Teſtament, which our Age and others may ſee fulfilled, and therefore are under the conviction of this <hi>Teſtimony</hi> equally.</p>
            <p>I mean, We of this, and every Age, are under the Convictions of that Revelation which the <hi>Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> has atteſted in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> (and therefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it has ſo atteſted;) as much as thoſe who liv'd in the daies of the Prophets, or in the Age of Miracles; for elſe I ſee not how <hi>Abraham</hi>'s anſwer to <hi>Dives</hi> is good; nay certainly, Poſterity is better enabled to judge of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> than the Age in which it firſt appear'd. And this, after the Canon of <hi>Scripture</hi> ſhut up, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally receiv'd, renders all New light, and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Inſpiration, not only ſuſpected, but perfectly need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41255:16"/>
            <p>The deſign of my Diſcourſe is chiefly this, to ſhew, That the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> thus explain'd, which ſo apparently runs parallel to the whole lines of <hi>Scriptural Revelation,</hi> doth moſt rationally convince us, and all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, of the <hi>Divine Truth of that Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if ſo, we gain two Points, not only of great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage alwaies, but moſt needful at this day; when <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> is either look'd out of countenance by <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Scepticiſm;</hi> or looks itſelf we know not whither, by the diſtortions of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Phanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt Point we gain is, To confirm our <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> in general upon moſt rational and accountable grounds, that it may endure the concuſſions and mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the World.</p>
            <p>The Second is, To confirm the Divine Authority of the Scriptures in particular, as our <hi>Sure Rule</hi> both of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Duty,</hi> for if we confeſs (as cannot be deny'd, till ſome other be produc'd as able) that the <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> was Author of the Predictions in Scripture; what reaſon can we have againſt the <hi>Inſtitution of life Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd?</hi> It being in all mens allowance unreaſonably unjuſt, To allow the Teſtimony of the <hi>Record</hi> in one part that it declares, and not in another; unleſs we can, better than by bold affirming, prove it in that part cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.</p>
            <p>To draw theſe Points out to the greater advantages, let me reflect upon this Diſcourſe, and infer Three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the great deſign of our Merciful Creator in giving this Teſtimony, is mens conviction in order to the Faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Obedience of Jeſus.</hi> For in its moſt plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful effuſion, and powerful operation, this was its firſt grand end, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>It ſhall convince the World,</hi> John 16. 18. which, when it has done, the <hi>Revelation</hi> itſelf becomes the undoubted Rule, as to Believers; but they who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41255:16"/> the whole Revelation, are principally to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd by this Teſtimony; which I have aſſerted to be moſt demonſtrative and ſatisfactory; and ſuch ſurely our Saviour thought it himſelf. <hi>I have told you before, that when its come to paſs ye may believe.</hi> Joh. 13. 19. and 16. 4.</p>
            <p>Whether then the Unbelievers, who pretend to a <hi>Primogeniture</hi> in Wit and Reaſon, having this convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on offer'd them under all the advantages of <hi>Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons fulfill'd,</hi> more than the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> had; as the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Scepticks</hi> of our Age; may not by aſcribing all to a cheat, <hi>ſin againſt the Holy Ghost,</hi> as well as they in <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. is a queſtion I will not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely determine in the affirmative; but ought not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks to be carried in the negative ſo <hi>dogmatically,</hi> as by the Authors of our Age it has; who (led, I believe, <note place="margin">Hales, &amp;c.</note> by their own native tenderneſs and benignity) have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, there's no Meridian for that Sin to appear in, now the Age of <hi>Miracles</hi> is paſt.</p>
            <p>To confirm the <hi>Faith of Jeſus,</hi> the Spirit both of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Prophecy</hi> was given Believers, as the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> and <hi>Jeſus</hi> foretold: and the manifeſt effects of this remain unto this day as <hi>foretold,</hi> in the Converſion of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> nay, all Events by <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Prophetical Writings and Apoſtolical, <hi>foretold,</hi> anſwer their Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, (to inſtance in the caſe of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation;) Therefore not only <hi>Jeſus</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> but the Revelation or Doctrine by them preach'd is confirm'd by it to be Divine, and that as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly as the Divine Spirit can <hi>demonstrate.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies, it <hi>did demonſtrate,</hi> and I think it can, as effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as any <hi>Mathematician</hi> in the Univerſe; whence I conclude, 'tis no defect in the Argument, but Brutality in the recipient obſtructs its force.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41255:17"/>
            <p>Secondly, I infer, That ſeeing the deſign of this <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony</hi> was, and is, man's Conviction in order to the <hi>Faith of Jeſus,</hi> there is ſomething in man capable of Conviction, even before he can be ſaid to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Nothing in Man being capable of Divine conviction, but the faculty of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> I infer, That the <hi>Faith of Jeſus</hi> is, and ought to be a <hi>Rational Faith.</hi> For the declining this Propoſition has encourag'd men of Parts, and lovers of Pleaſures, to decline <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> or men of weak Reaſon and ſtrong Imagination, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it into an Enthuſiaſtick and Phantaſtical thing.</p>
            <p>And to give this account for the Myſteries of Faith, that the <hi>Prime Verity</hi> has affirm'd them, as 'tis all we can without vanity give in this ſtate: ſo, if conſider'd, 'tis as good and rational as of any other knowledge we pretend to, for 'tis <hi>demonſtrable,</hi> that the laſt reſolution of <note place="margin">See <hi>Job</hi> 38. 4, 5, &amp;c. and 24, 25, &amp;c.</note> our Knowledge, of all other things, muſt upon a through ſcrutiny be into the <hi>Firſt Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many more than the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> think the want of <hi>Miracles</hi> mitigates the Crime of <hi>Infidelity,</hi> which to me ſeems but <hi>Dives</hi>'s vain opinion, for if men will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Teſtimony of the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy,</hi> neither will they believe <hi>Miracles,</hi> as being a Conviction that's eaſier ſhifted, than this which <hi>conſidered</hi> is more argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative; becauſe Reaſon may with ſome colour ſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the one, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did, than they can the other, for the proof of which I refer to <hi>John</hi> 5. 49.</p>
            <p>For I can never conceive that <hi>Miracles</hi> are of any ſignification, but as they addreſs to Reaſon to give it ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, <hi>i. e.</hi> as they prove the atteſtation of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi> and argue the Commiſſion to be from God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Seal is to it. For, to think that <hi>Miracles</hi> are terminated in the ſenſes, or deſigns any further upon them, than only to <hi>Excite the Intellect</hi> to a Judicious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41255:17"/> is to think that ſomething may be wrought upon a Beaſt by a <hi>Demonſtration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is the proper <hi>Mathematical Demonſtration,</hi> in Scheme of any ſignification, as 'tis terminated in ſight alone; for then the <hi>Elephant,</hi> that was taught to draw <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pliny,</hi> Nat. hiſt. lib. 8. cap. 3.</note> the <hi>Greek</hi> Alphabet, might have been taught as well to <hi>demonſtrate;</hi> but as thereby it helps to preſent convictive Truth to Reaſon: ſo that whatever convinceth Reaſon ſatisfactorily, attains the end of Demonſtration.</p>
            <p>Now all <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> though uſher'd in by ſenſe, (for the ſtupidity's ſake of our dull Underſtanding, which otherwaies will hardly be awaken'd;) yet ever made its application to Reaſon; therefore ſaies the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Shew your ſelves men,</hi> with reference to this very <note place="margin">Iſal. 46. 8, 9, 10. Luk. 12. 56. 2 Theſſ. 3. 2.</note> Argument of <hi>Prediction. Why do ye not of your ſelves judge what is right,</hi> ſaies Jeſus. <hi>Pray that we may be delivered from unreaſonable men, for all men have not Faith,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Neither is this <hi>Pelagianizing</hi> at all; I acknowledge the neceſſity of God's Supernatural Grace, and that <hi>Faith</hi> is his gift: 'tis poſſible it may be rejected, but the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that induce to it are moſt cogent; becauſe of God's making, not our own; what we do, is but to ſhew our ſelves men, <hi>i. e.</hi> to exert the Faculties with which he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du'd us in the firſt Inſtitution of our Nature, and with which he is ever ready to concur by his <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then whatever convinces <hi>Reaſon</hi> moſt, confirms <hi>Faith</hi> beſt, and <hi>Faith</hi> being ſo confirm'd, is the <hi>higheſt Reaſon</hi> in the World; for becauſe its <hi>light</hi> and <hi>diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries</hi> proceed (as my Reaſon tells me) from a more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring <hi>Intellect</hi> than mine own, 'tis moſt reaſonable, that it ſhould ſuperſede all the <hi>oppoſit</hi> acts of my own Mind, and leaves me no Inquiry, but whether the Spirit of God has ſaid ſo, or no; which ſufficiently diſcountenances all <hi>Socinianiſm.</hi> For it will not follow by any Rule of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41255:18"/> 
               <hi>Reaſon,</hi> That things are <hi>therefore</hi> true, or falſe, becauſe I can, or cannot comprehend them, (this were for our <hi>Reaſon</hi> to make it ſelf God,) but becauſe they are, or are not atteſted by the <hi>Prime Verity;</hi> how far ſoever they may exceed the <hi>Idaeal</hi> comprehenſions of our own finite Faculties; as the diſcoveries of <hi>Infinity</hi> neceſſarily muſt do, and in theſe all Chriſtian Myſteries conſiſt.</p>
            <p>So that Faith without Reaſon is fancy, as Reaſon op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Faith is phrenzy. For all the Myſteries which Goſpel Chriſtianity has made neceſſary, this is good and ſufficient Reaſon, <hi>God has plainly reveal'd them,</hi> and other matters beſide Myſteries, are evidently true from their congruity with our own reaſonable minds; as the excellency and goodneſs of its Precepts, and the nobleneſs of its End. And now, if upon theſe grounds we have that due honour for our Chriſtian Faith to aſſert it <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> as well as <hi>Holy;</hi> then 'twill follow, That no man of Parts, that's willing to conſider (and <hi>Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> ſignifie nothing elſe) the <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus,</hi> is Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious; but he that is <hi>Irrational.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For no Intereſt oppoſit to that of <hi>Jeſus</hi> can produce this Teſtimony, unleſs it be to its own overthrow. And therefore the grand Intereſts oppoſit or deſtructive to thoſe of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> will alwaies diſſemble and pretend this Teſtimony; <hi>Thou art Peter, upon this Rock will I build; To thee I give the Keys, feed my ſheep;</hi> ſo the <hi>Papal</hi> on one hand: or on the other hand (though in truth they are coincident,) <hi>They ſhall be all taught of God,</hi> and that's Infallible; ſo the <hi>Enthuſiaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My meaning is, That which endangers true Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, is ſome Evil within its own Profeſſion or Pale. And though there be a numerous brood of Offenders herein; yet there are Three who mainly threaten that <hi>Religion</hi> amongſt our ſelves, which God's wonderful Providence has preſerv'd ſo long; and we ſeem ſolicitous that it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41255:18"/> might be longer; and they are, in my apprehenſion, theſe Three, the <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and the <hi>vicious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, i. e.</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> the <hi>Ill-believers,</hi> and the <hi>Ill-livers,</hi> allowing Vice its due latitude.</p>
            <p>And theſe Three ſerve the mutual deſigns of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though as 'tis very ſubtil, <hi>Popery</hi> gets the laſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; for <hi>Vice</hi> begets <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> and <hi>Atheiſm</hi> at length devolves to <hi>Popery:</hi> for Ill-livers, 'tis their intereſt to be Unbelievers, and they that through the vice of Opinions and Sects have been alwaies unſtable, are very near the brink of this Precipice; ſo <hi>Vice</hi> begets <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> But becauſe to outſtrip the <hi>Devil</hi> and not believe at all, is impoſſible long to continue, and <hi>Religion</hi> in general is ſo planted in Nature, that it will recur and keep the field; therefore the moſt corrupt <hi>Religion</hi> in ſpecial, is fitteſt at laſt to be choſen; and ſo <hi>Atheiſm</hi> devolves to <hi>Popery,</hi> and ſends ſo many <hi>Newgate-Converts</hi> to <hi>Tyburne,</hi> as that party boaſts of.</p>
            <p>But Conviction without bitterneſs is all the <hi>Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> I ſhall tender from this diſcourſe, and that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the Three aboveſaid.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To <hi>Atheiſm</hi> thus. If the <hi>Scriptural Revelation,</hi> which is the Chriſtian Inſtitution be not to be believ'd, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the World is; for he that conſiders it as becomes a reaſonable man, and yet disbelieves it, rejects the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the <hi>Prime Verity,</hi> as I prov'd before: And ſet this aſide, let the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> prove his Senſes, or any thing in the World true if he can.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To <hi>Popery</hi> (which is that part of pretended Chriſtianity which is peculiar to them of the preſent <hi>Roman Communion</hi> and none elſe.)</p>
            <p>I apply the Conviction of this diſcourſe thus.</p>
            <p>That if any Religion ſo call'd, overthrow the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Natural Religion; as by introducing <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and ſubverting the common Notions of Good and Evil;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41255:19"/> then by the grand Rule of <hi>trying Spirits,</hi> 'tis moſt infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly an Impoſture. To make good which Charge againſt <hi>Popery</hi> in each particular Doctrine or Practice by that Church eſpouſed, as I may not now eſſay: So I think 'tis ſufficient to conſider the many bloody Plots it has hatcht to promote it ſelf, and to weigh the whole Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Jeſuits Caſuiſtical Divinity;</hi> for never did any pretended <hi>Religion</hi> ſo boldly and palpably refix the common and natural ſentiments of Good and Evil, as that has done. And God grant that no Profeſſion amongſt our ſelves by thirſting after New light and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, pretending to differ from them, may yet ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolize with them in this particular.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, To the <hi>vicious Proteſtant,</hi> or Member (as he calls himſelf) of the <hi>Church Reform'd</hi> the Conviction applies itſelf; for ſuch an one ſtands ſelf-condemn'd; a <hi>good Believer</hi> (as he thinks himſelf) and a <hi>bad Liver,</hi> being one of the greateſt abſurdities in the World; and may not this be fear'd as much as <hi>Popery?</hi> for that makes but Men, this makes God our Enemy.</p>
            <p>We talk much at this day of uniting different Parties joyntly diſclaiming <hi>Popery,</hi> and God grant it may ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to good effect; but if it be an Union in matters of <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> I hope they'l let us of the <hi>Church of England</hi> by Law eſtabliſht, know what <hi>Faith</hi> they are of, as they know ours: For methinks all, or moſt Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in the World might be reconcil'd but one, and that's the difference between <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil;</hi> and this indeed is eternally irreconcileable.</p>
            <p>The beſt method then of Uniting us who pretend to the <hi>Reform'd Religion,</hi> is to carry on that part of it which is moſt needful: not to Reform the Church, but the Members of it, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Evils we are guilty of againſt the Rules of it: and this is more in Our power than our Governours, elſe I would not mention it; but then, as
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41255:19"/> I ſaid before, <hi>Evil</hi> and <hi>Vice</hi> muſt have its due latitude, which takes in giddy and Enthuſiaſtick Opinions, as well as ſenſual and ſinful practices: for there is a <hi>Filthineſs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 1.</note> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> as well as of the <hi>Fleſh;</hi> I mean, ungovern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Spiritual Pride and Intellectual Debaucheries, as well as Senſual.</p>
            <p>And would all ſorts of People joyntly diſclaiming <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> ſet themſelves ſincerely and humbly about this great work of <hi>Reformation;</hi> it would certainly diſpoſe their hearts to the Union of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>good Affection;</hi> though it might not in every particular mould their heads into an Unity of <hi>Notion:</hi> And without this Unity in <hi>good Affection,</hi> 'tis ſtrange, if a Church or Kingdom ſo divided ſhould ſtand.</p>
            <p>In a word, That our <hi>Faith</hi> in Jeſus might be Rational and laſting, I have preſt the beſt Argument of <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> and <hi>Conviction</hi> I know. That it may work by <hi>Love,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Chriſtian Affection,</hi> ſhall be my Prayer, and ought to be all our Endeavours, <hi>Till we all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 13.</note> 
               <hi>come in the unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the stature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Which God of his infinite mercy grant, by directing and ſucceeding theſe and all the Miniſteries of his Appointment, through the continual Bleſſings of his Holy Spirit, for the ſake of Jeſus our Lord; To whom, with the Father and the Divine Spirit, be Praiſe, and Honour, and Glory eternal.</hi> Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
